<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>A breef and sommarie discourse vpon the entended voyage to the hethermoste partes of America: Written by Captaine Carleill in Aprill 1583. for the better inducement to satisfie suche marchauntes of the Moscouian Companie and others, as in disburcyng their money towardes the furniture of the present charge: doe demaunde forthwith a present returne of gaine: albeit their saied perticuler disburcements are required but in verie slender sommes: The highest beeyng twentie and fiue pounde. The second at twelve pound ten shillynges. And y[e] lowest at sixe pound fiue shillinges.</title>
            <author>Carleill, Christopher, 1551?-1593.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1583</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 35 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 9 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2011-12">2011-12 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">B01022</idno>
            <idno type="STC">STC 4626.5</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC S91357</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">44920321</idno>
            <idno type="OCLC">ocm 44920321</idno>
            <idno type="VID">173767</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. B01022)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 173767)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1475-1640 ; 2096:7)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>A breef and sommarie discourse vpon the entended voyage to the hethermoste partes of America: Written by Captaine Carleill in Aprill 1583. for the better inducement to satisfie suche marchauntes of the Moscouian Companie and others, as in disburcyng their money towardes the furniture of the present charge: doe demaunde forthwith a present returne of gaine: albeit their saied perticuler disburcements are required but in verie slender sommes: The highest beeyng twentie and fiue pounde. The second at twelve pound ten shillynges. And y[e] lowest at sixe pound fiue shillinges.</title>
                  <author>Carleill, Christopher, 1551?-1593.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[16] p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>J. Kingston?</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>[S.l. :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1583?]</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Imprint information from STC (2nd ed.).</note>
                  <note>Title within border of printer's ornaments.</note>
                  <note>Signatures: A-B⁴.</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of original in: Dulwich College Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Carleill, Christopher, 1551?-1593.</term>
               <term>Trading companies --  England --  Early works to 1800.</term>
               <term>America --  Discovery and exploration --  British --  Early works to 1800.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2010-08</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-09</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-02</date>
            <label>Mona Logarbo</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-02</date>
            <label>Mona Logarbo</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-06</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="half_title">
            <pb facs="tcp:173767:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:173767:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <p>¶ <hi>A breef and ſommarie diſcourſe <hi>vp<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pon the entended <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>oyage to the</hi>
               </hi> hethermoſte partes of <hi>America:</hi> Written by Captaine <hi>Carleill</hi> in Aprill <hi>1583.</hi> for the better inducement to ſatiſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fie ſuche Marchauntes of the <hi>Moſcouian</hi> Companie and others, as in diſburcyng their money towardes the furniture of the pre<gap reason="illegible" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>nt charge: doe demaunde forth<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>with a meſent returne of gaine: al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>beit their ſaied perticuler diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>burcements are required but in verie ſlender ſommes:</p>
            <p>The higheſt beeyng twentie and fiue pounde. The ſeconde at twelue pound ten ſhillynges. And y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> loweſt at ſixe pound fiue ſhillinges.</p>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="prospectus_for_voyage">
            <pb facs="tcp:173767:2" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <head>Captaine Carleills diſcourſe</head>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">W</seg>Hen the Goldſmith deſireth to finde the certaine goodneſſe of a peece of golde, which is newly offered vnto hym, he pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſently bryngeth the ſame to the Touch<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtone: whereby comparyng the ſhowe or touche of this newe peece with the touch or ſhewe of that whiche he knoweth of olde, he forthwith is able to iudge what the valewe is of that, which is newly offered vnto hym. After the exſample wherof I haue thought it good to make ſome briefe repetition of the perticuler eſtate of many other forraine Voyages and trades alreadie frequented and knowne vnto vs, wherby you maie be the better able to conceiue and iudge what certaine likeli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hood of good there is to be expected in the Voyage, whiche is preſently reco<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>mended vnto your knowledge and reſolution.</p>
            <p>And firſt to laie doune that of <hi>Moſcouia,</hi> whoſe beginnyng is yet in the remembrance of many. It is well knowne that what by the charges of the firſt diſcouerie, and by the greate giftes beſtowed on the Emperor and his Nobilitie, together with the leaud dealing of ſome their ſeruauntes, who thought themſelues ſafe enough from orderly puniſhment. It coſt the Companie aboue fower ſkore thouſande poundes, before it could be brought to any profitable reckoning. And now that after ſo long a pacience, and ſo greate a burthen of expences. the ſame beganne to frame to ſome good courſe and commo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dity: It faleth to very tickliſh tearmes, and to as ſlender like<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lihood of any further goodneſſe as any other trade that may be named. For firſt the eſtate of thoſe Countreis and the Em<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perours dealinges, are thinges more fickle then are by euery bodie vnderſtoode. Next, the Dutchmen are there ſo crept in, as thei daiely augment their trade thether, which maie well confirme that vncertentie of the Emperours diſpoſition to keepe promiſe with our Nation. Thirdly, the qualitie of the voyage, ſuche as it may not bee performed but once the yere. Fourthly, the charges of all Ambaſſadours betweene that Prince &amp; her Maieſtie, are alwaies borne by the Marchants
<pb facs="tcp:173767:2" rendition="simple:additions"/>ſtocke. And laſtly, the daunger of the Kyng of Denmarke, who beſides that preſently he is like to enforce a tribute on vs, hath likewiſe an aduauntage vpon our Shippes in their voyage, either homewardes or outwardes whenſoeuer he li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſteth to take the opportunitie.</p>
            <p>The bad dealynges of the Eſterlynges are ſufficiently knowne to be ſuche towardes our Marchaunts of that trade, as thei doe not onely offer them many iniuries ouerlong to be written, but doe ſeeke all the meanes thei can, to depriue them wholy of their occupiyng that waie: and to the ſame purpoſe haue of late, cleane debarred them their accuſtomed and auncient priuileges in all their greate Townes.</p>
            <p>The traffiques into Turkie, beſides that by ſome it is thought a harde poinct to haue ſo muche familiarity with the profeſſed and obſtinate Enemie of Chriſt: It is likewiſe a voyage whiche can not bee made but at the deuotion, and as it were in the daunger of many States, who for ſondrie re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpectes are apt to quarrell with vs vppon ſudden occaſions. And the preſentes to be giuen awaie in Turkie this yere coſt litle leſſe then two thouſande poundes.</p>
            <p>As for the trades into all the partes of Italie, it maie eaſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly be conſidered by euery one of iudgement, that the ſame ſta<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
               <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deth in the like termes touching the paſſages, as that of Tur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kie, and that many tymes our Shippes beeyng taken in the waie by the <hi>Galleis</hi> of <hi>Barbary,</hi> our poore Mariners after the loſſe of their goodes and trauaile, are ſett at ſuche exceſſiue Rau<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ſomes before thei can be freed of their ſlauerie: as for the moſt parte thei are no way able to diſcharge: as for Example at this inſtaunt there are ſome priſoners poore ordinary Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riners, for whoſe releaſing there muſt be paied two hundred Duckets the man, for ſome three hundred, yea, fower or fiue hu<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>dred Duckets the man for ſome of the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>. And how enuiouſly thei doe already oppoſe them ſelues againſt our frequenting into their partes, maie appeare by the late cuſtomes which thei haue impoſed aſwell vppon our Engliſh Marchaundize whiche wee bryng them, as alſo vpon ſuche their Marchaun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dize
<pb facs="tcp:173767:3"/>whiche we fetche from them.</p>
            <p>The trade into <hi>Barbury</hi> groweth likewiſe to worſe tear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mes then before tymes: and when it was at the beſt our Mar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chauntes haue beene in daunger of all their goodes thei had there, whenſoeuer it happened the Ryng to die. For vntill a new were choſe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, the liberty of al diſcordered perſons is ſuch, as thei ſpoile &amp; wro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>g who<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> thei liſt without any redreſſe at al.</p>
            <p>Touchyng Spaine and Portugall, with whom wee haue very greate trade, and muche the greater, by meanes of their ventyng a good parte of our wares into their <hi>Jndies,</hi> as alſo of the prouiſion thei haue from the ſame, wherwith are made manye of our returnes from them againe. It falleth out that twiſe the yere ordinarily we ſende our Flates into thoſe par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tes: So that whenſoeuer the Ryng of Spaine liſteth to take the opportunity, he maie at theſe ſeaſons depriue vs not only of a greate nomber of our very good Shippes, but alſo of our honeſteſt, and ableſt ſort of Marriners that are to be found in our whole Realme againe: which is a matter of no ſmall con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſequence: for it is to bee noted, that when he ſhall take a quar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rell in hande, though it be but his owne perticulerly, yet hath he the meanes to put in hazarde aſwell thoſe our Shippes which are in his owne Countreis of Spaine and Portugall, as alſo all others whiche ſhall be bounde to any the partes of all Italie or of Turkie either. And further whoſoeuer he bee that is but ſo meanly affected in Religion, as of neceſſitie be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>commeth euery ordinarie man and good Chriſtian to be, can not but be agreeued in his harte to conſider, that his children and ſeruaunts whom he deſireth to haue well brought vp, are in theſe trades of Spaine and Portugall and all Italie, for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ced to deny their owne profeſſion, and made to acquaint them ſelues with that which the Parentes and Maiſters doe vtter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly denie and refuſe, yea which many of them doe in their own hartes abhorre as a deteſtable and moſt wicked doctrine.</p>
            <p>But who ſhall looke into the quality of this voyage, beyng directed to the latitude of <hi>40.</hi> degrees, or there aboutes of that hithermoſt part of <hi>America,</hi> ſhal finde it hath as many poinc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tes
<pb facs="tcp:173767:3" rendition="simple:additions"/>of good moment belonging vnto it, as may almoſt be wi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhed for. As firſt it is to be vnderſtoode, that it is not any long courſe, for it may be performed to and from fower monethes, after the firſt diſcouery thereof: Secondly, that one wind ſuf<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fiſeth to make the paſſage; wheras moſt of your other voya<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ges of like length, are ſubiect to three or fower winds. Third<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lie, that it is to be performed at all tymes of the yere. Fo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>werthly, that the paſſage is vpon the high ſea, wherby you are not bound to the knowledge of daungers, on any other coaſt, more then of that Countrey, and of ours here at home. Fift<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lie, that thoſe partes of Englande and Irelande, whiche lye apteſt for the proceedyng outward, or homeward vpon this voyage, are verie well ſtored of goodlie Harbourghes. Sixt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly, that it is to be accompted of no daunger at al, as touching the power of any foraine Prince or State, when it is compa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red with any the beſt of all the other voyages before recited.</p>
            <p>And to the godlie mynded, it hath this comfortable com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>moditie, that in this trade, their Factours, bee thei their ſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uauntes or children, ſhall haue no inſtruction or confeſſions of Idolatrous Religion enforced vpon them, but contrarily ſhall bee at their free libertie of conſcience, and ſhall finde the ſame Religion exerciſed, whiche is moſt agreable vnto their parentes and Maiſters</p>
            <p>As for the Merchandizyng, whiche is the matter eſpeci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ally looked for, albeit that for the preſent, we are not certain<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly able to promiſe any ſuche like quantitie, as is now at the beſt tyme of the <hi>Moſcouian</hi> trade brought from thence: So likewiſe is there not demaunded any ſuche proportion of dai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly expences, as was at the firſt, and as yet is conſumed in that of <hi>Moſcouia</hi> and other. But when this of <hi>America</hi> ſhall haue been haunted and practized, thirtie yeres to an ende, as the o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther hath been, I doubte not by Gods grace, that for the tenne Shippes, that are now commonly employed once the yere into <hi>Moſcouia,</hi> there ſhall in this voyage twiſe tenne be im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ployed well, twiſe the yere at the leaſt. And if for the preſent tyme, there dooe fall out nothyng els to bee founde, then the
<pb facs="tcp:173767:4"/>bare Fiſhyng, yet doubte I not after the firſt yeres planting, but by that matter only to ſerue half a dozen of your beſt ſort of ſhippes, although my ſupplie of people doe not followe me ſo ſubſtancially, as in all reaſon maie be well looked for.</p>
            <p>But when it is aſked what maie bee hoped from thence af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter ſome yeres, it is firſt to bee conſidered, that this ſituation in <hi>40.</hi> degrees, ſhalbe verie apte to gather the commodities, either of thoſe partes whiche ſtande to the Southward of it, as alſo of thoſe whiche are to the Northward.</p>
            <p>In the Northerlie maie be expected, not onely an eſpeciall good fiſhing for Salmon, Codde, and Whales, but alſo any other ſuche co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>modities, as the Eaſterne Countre is doe yeeld vs now: as Pitche, Tarre, Hempe, and therof Cordage, Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtes, Loſſhe hides, riche Furres, and other ſuche like, without beyng in any ſort beholdyng to a Kyng of Denmarke, or o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther Prince or State, that ſhalbe in ſuch ſort able to co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>maund our ſhippes at their pleaſure, as thoſe dooe at this daie, by meanes of their ſtraight, paſſages, and ſtrong Shippyng.</p>
            <p>As for thoſe partes which lye Weſt, and to the Southwar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>des, it maie well be hoped thei will yeeld wines with a ſmall helpe, ſince the grapes doe grow there of themſelues already very faire, and in great abundance. Oliues beyng once plan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted, will yeeld the like Oile as Spain and Italy. The Coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trey people beyng made to know, that for Waxe and Honie, we will giue them ſuche triflyng thynges, as thei deſire of vs, and ſhewyng them once the meanes, how to prouide the ſame, the labour thereof beyng ſo light, no doubt but in ſhort tyme thei will earneſtly care to haue the ſame in good quan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>titie for vs. Beſides what greate likelihoode there is of good meanes to make Salt, which may ſerue for y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> fiſhing of thoſe partes, maie well enough appeare vnto them, who can iudge the quality of ſuch places, as are required to make y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> ſame in.</p>
            <p>Thus muche for the beginnyng, becauſe thei may be had with an eaſie kinde of trauaill. But when it maie haue plea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed God, to eſtabliſhe our people there any ſuche tyme, as thei maie haue planted amongeſte them, in ſondrie partes of the
<pb facs="tcp:173767:4"/>Countrey, and that by gentle and familiar entreatyng them, thei bee made to ſee, what is better for them, then thei doe as yet vnderſtande of, and that in ſo many ſortes of occaſious, as were infinite to be ſet doune. It is to be aſſuredly hoped, that thei will daiely by little &amp; little, forſake their barbarous, and ſauage liuyng, and grow to ſuche order and ciuilitie with vs, as there maie be wel expected from thence no leſſe quantitie, and diuerſity of Marchandize,<note place="margin">This is ſpoke<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> vpon the o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pinion which by ſome is conceiued that Irelande is not ſuffeted to be redu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ced to that perfection whiche it might be, leaſt one dai<gap reason="illegible" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> by chaunce reuoltyng fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> the Crowne it might proue an ouerſtro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>g partie to be ſo nere an e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nemie vnto England.</note> then is now had out of Dutch<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lande, Italie, Fraunce, or Spaigne. And as the borderyng neighbours, are commonly the apteſt to fall out with vs, ſo theſe partes, beyng ſomewhat further remote, are the liker to take, or giue leſſe occaſion of diſquiet. But when it is conſide<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red, that thei are our owne kindred, and eſteemed our owne Countrey Nation whiche haue the gouernement: meanyng by thoſe who ſhalbe there planted, who ca<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>looke for any other then the dealyng of moſt louing, and moſte aſſured freendes.</p>
            <p>There are further to be conſidered, theſe twoo pointes of good importaunce, concernyng the matter of trade. The one is, that by the good proſperyng of this action, there muſte of neceſſitie fall out, a verie liberall vtteraunce of our Engliſhe Clothes, into a maine Countrey, deſcribed to be bigger then all <hi>Europe,</hi> the larger parte whereof bendyng to the North<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ward, ſhall haue wonderfull greate vſe of our ſaied Engliſhe Clothes, after thei ſhall ouce come to knowe the commoditie therof. The like will be alſo of many other thinges, ouerma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny to be reconed, which are made here by our Artificers &amp; la<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bouryng people, and of neceſſity muſt be prouided fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> hence.</p>
            <p>The other is, if there bee any poſſible meanes, to finde a Sea paſſage, or other freſhe water courſe, whiche mate ſerue in ſome reaſonable and conuenient ſorte, to tranſporte our Marchandize into the Eaſt <hi>Indian</hi> Sea, through any of theſe Northerly partes of <hi>America,</hi> it ſhalbe ſoneſt and moſte aſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſuredly performed by theſe who ſhall inhabite, and firſt grow into familiaritie with the Inlande people.</p>
            <p>What Minerall matter maie fall out to be founde, is a thing leaſt in ſuſpence, vntil ſome better knowledge, becauſe
<pb facs="tcp:173767:5"/>there be many menne, who hauing long ſince, expected ſome profites herein, vpon the great promiſes that haue been made them, and beyng as yet in no poincte ſatiſfied, doe therevpon conceiue, that thei bee but woordes pourpoſely caſte out, for the inducyng of menne to bee the more willyng to furniſhe their money, towardes the charge of the firſt diſcouerie.</p>
            <p>But now to aunſwere ſome others, who beginne with an other obiection, ſaiyng: That it is not for the Marchauntes purſe, to continue the charges of tranſportyng and plantyng: and that ſince theſe hundred menne, whiche are now to bee planted, will coſte fower thouſande pounde, it is then to bee thought, that the charge of a farre greater nomber, will be al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſo a farre greater ſome of money. Wherevnto I aunſwere, that in all atemptes vnknowne, eſpecially ſuche a one as is this, wherewith wee are preſently in hande, the firſt charges are commonly aduentured in more deſperate kind, then thoſe that folowe vppon ſome better knowledge: and therewith it falleth out, that whereas one aduentureth in the firſte enter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>priſe, an hundred for that one will of themſelues bee willyng, and deſirous to aduenture in the next, if there be neuer ſo lit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tle more apparaunce, that the entended matter is by ſome knowledge of our owne, found true in ſome poinctes of our firſte preſumption.<note place="margin">The ewer of Mettall brought by Maiſter Fro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>biſher, cauſed two ſeuerall Supplies tho two yeares next follo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wyng, where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>of the latter was of xiiij. tall Shippes.</note> The examples are many, and maie eaſily bee remembred by thoſe who bee Marchantes, euen in their ordinarie and daiely trades, as well as in extraordinarie at<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>temptes, whiche of late yeres haue fallen into thoſe tearmes of ſome likelihoode, as is aboue ſaied. So then no doubt, but when certaine reportes ſhalbe brought by them, who directly come from thence: that ſuch a Cou<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>trey and people, thei haue themſelues ſeen, as is by vs ſpoke<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> of, but that then there will come forwarde a greater nomber of thoſe, who now neither haue hard any thing of the matter, as alſo of others, who pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſently make ſuche friuolous ſcruple, as will not otherwiſe be ſatiſfied, then by the reporte of ſaincte Thomas. I ſpeak not this by the Marchauntes, whom for their freedomes of trade, I would not haue preſſed to any further charge, then this firſt
<pb facs="tcp:173767:5"/>preparacion, but rather by ſuche as haue great affection, to hazarde the chaungyng of their eſtates,<note place="margin">Sir Fraunces Drake his paſſedge on<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly through the Iles of Molucca, was cauſe of a preparation thither of ſeuenteene thouſande poundes, whereof there was not a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>boue fiue or ſix thouſand in Marchaun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dize, the reſt in other char<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ges of Ship<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pyng and ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>penſiue pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uiſion.</note> and would be well content to goe in the Voyage, if thei might onely bee aſſured that there is ſuche a Countrey, and that their money ſhould not be waſted to nothyng in the preparations. The right exa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mination of this poincte, muſt bee the contrary ſequell of the common Poruerbe, <hi>Nothyng venture, nothyng haue,</hi> ſo on the other ſide by venturyng, many greate good proffites are fou<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>d out, to the wonderful benefite of the common weale, and to thoſe eſpecially in priuate, who take on the hazarde of their life and trauaill, or ſubſtance in the firſt attemptes, and there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore I would wiſhe that thei who (God bee thanked) are well able to ſpare that, whiche is required of eche one towardes the vndertakyng of this aduenture, bee well content and wil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lyng to employe the ſame, ſince the ſequell in good and ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtanciall reaſon dooeth promiſe, not onely a greate commodi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tie in perticuler to the Marchaunte, who ſhall here at home exerciſe the trade of Marchaundize: But alſo to an infinite nomber of other, who preſently liue in poore eſtate, and maie by takyng the opportunitie of this diſcouerie, alter the ſame to a farre better degree. Wherefore to make ſome concluſion vpon this poincte of the Marchauntes miſdoubt, who ſuſpec<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teth leaſt this firſt diſburcement, without returne of preſent gaine, ſhould not bee all his charge, but that afterwardes he might yet further bee vrged to continue the like againe, as hath happened in the diſcouerie of the <hi>Moſcouian</hi> trade. It maie ſuffice to conſider, that this is not an action, whiche con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cerneth onely the Marchau<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>tes perticulerly, but a grea<gap reason="illegible" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> deale more the generall ſorte of people throughout all Englande: And that when ſuche relation ſhalbe returned, as that it maie bee founde a matter worthie the folowyng, the whole gene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ralitie will not refuſe to contribute towards the furtherance thereof, rather then it ſhould ſincke, for wante of any reaſona<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble ſupplie. But as it is a very little tyme, ſince I haue been throughlie reſolued, to trie my fortune in the matter, ſo is it more then tyme, the preparation were in hande already, and
<pb facs="tcp:173767:6"/>therefore no fit tyme now, to make any nomber of ignoraunt men to vnderſtande with reaſon, the circumſtance that belon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>geth to a matter of ſo greate conſideration and importance.</p>
            <p>To thoſe who haue any forwarde myndes in wel doyng, to the generalitie of mankinde, I ſaie this muche more, that Chriſtian charitie doeth as greatly perſwade the furtherance of this action, as any other that maie bee laied before vs, in as muche as thereby, wee ſhall not onely dooe a moſte excellent worke, in reſpect of reducyng the ſauage people, to Chriſtia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nitie and ciuilitie, but alſo in reſpect of our poore ſorte of peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple, whiche are verie many amongſt vs, liuyng altogether vnprofitable, and often tymes to the great diſquiet of the bet<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter ſorte. For who knoweth not, how by the long peace, hap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pie health, and bleſſed plentifulneſſe, wherewith GOD hath endewed this Realme, that the people is ſo mightely encrea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed, as a great nomber beyng brought vp, duryng their youth in their parentes houſes, without any inſtruction how to gett their liuinges, after their parents deceaſe, are driuen to ſome neceſſitie, whereby verie often, for want of better education thei fall into ſondrie diſorders, and ſo the good ſorte of people, as I ſaied before, are by them ordinarily troubled, and them ſelues ledd on, to one ſhamefull ende or other, wheras if there might bee founde ſome ſuche kinde of imploymente, as this would bee no doubt but a greater part of them would be with held, fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> fallyng into ſuche vile deedes: and in ſteade thereof, proue greatly ſeruiceable in thoſe affaires, where thei might be ſo imploied. This I ſpeake of myne owne experience, ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uyng ſeen diuers come ouer to the warres of the lawe Coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tries, duryng my rſidence in the ſame, who here had been ve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rie euill and idle liuers, and by ſome little continuance with vs, haue growne to bee verie induſtrious in their facultie, whiche I ca<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> aſſure you, was a more painfull maner of liuing, then in this action is like to fall out, and withall to a purpoſe of farre leſſe valew, in reſpect of their perticuler recompe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ce, then with an aſſured kinde of good hope is loked for in this.</p>
            <p>Thus you ſee in euery poincte, that maie be wiſhed for, in
<pb facs="tcp:173767:6"/>a good action and voyage, there is matter and reaſon enough to ſatiſfie the well diſpoſed. But now to growe ſomwhat ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rer the quicke, and to ſhowe you ſome greater apparaunce, then hath been yet ſpoken of touching the trade whiche is the onely ſubiect wherwith I doe meane to entermeddle at this tyme, becauſe my addreſſe hereby is cheifly to me<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> of ſuch like faculty: you may vnderſta<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>de by that foloweth, the circo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ſtance of a little diſcourſe, whiche doeth concerne theſe matters ve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry directly.</p>
            <p>In the yere <hi>1534.</hi> Iames Carthier of Deepe, made his firſt diſcouerie of thoſe partes of <hi>America,</hi> whiche lye to the Weſtwardes, and as it were on the backſide of newfounde<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>land. In whiche voyage his principall intention was to ſeeke out the paſſage, whiche he preſumed might haue been founde out, into the Eaſt Indian ſea, otherwiſe called the paſſage to <hi>Cathayo,</hi> but this yere he went no higher, then the Iſtandes of the aſſumption in the greate Baie of S. Laureuce, and ſo returned backe into Fraunce.</p>
            <p>The next yere followyng he went with greater prouiſion into the grand Bay againe, where he keeping the Northerly ſhore, ranne vp the greate Riuer that comes doune from <hi>Ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nada</hi> and other places, vntill at laſte with his ſmall Pinaces, hauyng lefte his greate Shippyng by the waie, he ariued at <hi>Fochelaga</hi> Toune, beeyng fiue hundred leagues within the entrance of the grande Baie. In whiche trauaill he had ſpent ſo muche of the yere, that it was now the moneth of October, and therefore thought it co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>uenient, for the better enformyng hymſelf at large in this diſcouerie, to Winter it out in thoſe partes, which he did at a place called by himſelf holy Croſſe. This Winter fell out to bee a verie long and hard Winter, as many tymes the like happeneth with vs in theſe partes, and the ſauage people who for the moſte parte, make but a ſlender kinde of prouiſion, euen as it were fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> hand to mouth fell into ſome ſcarcitie of victualles; yet did thei not refuſe to ſerue the Frenchmen, with any thyng thei had all the Win<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter long, albeit at ſomwhat higher prices towardes the end,
<pb facs="tcp:173767:7"/>when the neede was moſte, as with our ſelues the like happe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neth at ſuche tymes. But when the Frenche had had their wantes ſerued all the yere, and that as yet thei ſawe not, any apparance of their entended matter, whiche was the diſcoue<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rie of the paſſage, and yet imaginyng by the ſignes where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>with the willyng people, endeuoured to declare their know<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledge in that poinct, that ſome good matter might bee had from them, if thei might haue been well vnderſtoode, they re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſolued with themſelues, to take ſome of the ſufficienteſt men of that Countrey home into Fraunce, and there to keepe the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> ſo long, as that hauyng once achieued the Frenche tongue, thei might declare more ſubſtancially their mynd, and know<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledge in the ſaied paſſage, concludyng this to be the meane of leaſt charge, of leaſt trauaile, and of leaſt hazarde. And when thei came to bethinke themſelues, who might bee meeteſt for it, thei determined to take the King, as the perſon who might bee beſt enformed of ſuche partes, as were ſomewhat remote from his owne Countrey, as alſo that for the reſpect of hym, the people would be alwaies readie, and content to doe them any further ſeruice, when it ſhould happen them to retourne thether againe about the diſcouerie. Thus the poore Kyng of the Countrey, with two or three others of his chief compa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nions commyng aboard the Frenche Shippes, being requi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red thether to a bancket, was traiterouſly caried awaie into Fraunce, where he liued fower yeares, and then dyed a Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtian there, as <hi>Theuet</hi> the Frenche Kynges Coſmographer doeth make mention. This outrage and iniurious dealyng, did put the whole countrey people into ſuche diſlike with the Frenche, as neuer ſince thei would admit any conuerſation, or familiaritie with them, vntill of late yeres, the olde matter beginnyng to growe out of mynd, and beyng the rather dra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wen on by giftes of many triflyng thynges, whiche were of greate value with them, thei are (as I ſaid) within theſe two or three yeares content againe to admitte a traffique,<note place="margin">The yere 1581.</note> whiche two yeares ſince, was begonne with a ſmall Barke of thirtie tunnes, whoſe retourne was founde ſo profitable, as the next
<pb facs="tcp:173767:7"/>yere followyng, beyng the laſt yeare, by thoſe Marchauntes, who meant to haue kept the trade ſecrete vnto themſelues, from any others of their owne Countrey men, there was hi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red a Shippe of fower ſcore tunnes out of the Ile of <hi>Jerſey,</hi> but not any one Mariner of that place, ſauyng a Shipboye. This Shippe made her retourne in ſuche ſorte, as that this yeare thei haue multiplied three Shippes to bee one of nine ſcore tunnes, an other of an hundred tunnes, and a third of fo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wer ſcore tunnes: whiche reporte is giuen by very ſubſtanci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>all and honeſt men of <hi>Plymouth,</hi> who ſawe the ſaied Shippes in readineſſe to departe on their Voyage, and were aboarde of ſome of them. Here is at this inſtant in the towne a man of <hi>Gerneſey, Lewis de <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>icke:</hi> who reporteth to haue credibly heard, that by this laſt yeares Voyage the Frenchmen got foreteene or fifteene hundred for euery one hundred. But how ſoeuer it bee, it carieth good likelihoode of ſome notable pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fite, in aſmuche as thei doe ſo greatly, and thus ſuddenly en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>creaſe the burthen and number of their Shippes this preſent yeare. Now, if in ſo little as two yeares tymes this voyage of the Northerne partes bee growne to ſuche good paſſe as hath been declared vnto you: it is worthe the thinkyng on to conſider what maie bee hoped for, from the Sotherne parte: whiche in all reaſon maie promiſe a greate deale more. And ſo as one who was neuer touchd with any indirect meanyng, I preſume to wiſhe and perſwade you to ſome better takyng of this matter to harte, as a thing which I doe verely thinke will turne to your greater and more aſſured commoditie, then you receiue by any other Voyage, as yet frequented of ſo ſhorte and ſafe a courſe as this hath: dealyng herein no other<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wiſe with you for your ſeueral ſmal ſommes, then I doe with my ſelf, bothe for more of myne owne, then is required of any one of you: beſides the hazard and trauell of my perſon, and the total imployment of my poore credite, whiche (I thanke God) hath hetherto paſſed clere and vnſpotted in mat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ters of greater importaunce and difficultie, then is like to fall out in this betweene you and mee.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="articles_of_contract_for_voyage">
            <pb facs="tcp:173767:8"/>
            <head>Articles ſet doune by the Comitties
<note place="margin">
                  <list>
                     <head>The Comit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ties.</head>
                     <item>Maiſter Al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derman Hart.</item>
                     <item>Maiſter Alder<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>man Spencer.</item>
                     <item>M. Hoddeſde<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>.</item>
                     <item>Mai. Willyam Burrowgh.</item>
                     <item>Mai. Slany.</item>
                     <item>M. Towerſon.</item>
                     <item>Ma. Stapers.</item>
                     <item>Maiſter Ihon Caſtelyn.</item>
                     <item>Mai. Leake.</item>
                  </list>
               </note>
appointed in the behalfe of the Companie of <hi>Moſcouian</hi> Marchaunts, to conferre with Maiſter <hi>Carleill,</hi> vpon his entended diſcoueries and attempt into the he<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thermoſt parties of <hi>America.</hi>
            </head>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">F</seg>Irſt, the Committies are well perſwaded that the Countrey wherevnto this action preten<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deth is very fruitfull, Inhabited with ſauedge people of a middle &amp; tractable diſpoſition. And that of all other places whiche are vnfrequen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted at this daie, it is the onely moſt fitteſt and moſt commodi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous for vs to entermeddle withall.</p>
            <p>The conuenienteſt maner of attemptyng this enterpriſe, is thought to be thus: That there ſhould be one hundred men conueied thether to remaine there one whole yeare: who with freendly entreatie of the people, may enter into better know<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledge of the particuler eſtate of the Countrey, and thereby gather what Commoditie maie be hereafter or preſently loo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ked for.</p>
            <p>The charge to tranſporte theſe hundred men, to victuall them, and to furniſhe them of Munition and other needefull thynges, will not bee leſſe then fower thouſande poundes: whereof hath beene very readily offered by the Citie of Bri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtoll one thouſande poundes, the reſide we beeyng three thou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſande poundes, remaineth to bee furniſhed by this Citie of London: or any others who will aduenture their money in this firſt preparation.</p>
            <p>The Comitties thinke it conuenient that a Priuſſedge ſhould be procured by Maiſter <hi>Carleill</hi> from her Maieſtie, by vertue whereof theſe Conditions and Articles followyng, maie be effectually prouided for.</p>
            <p>Firſt, that thei who ſhall diſburce their money for the firſt
<pb facs="tcp:173767:8"/>preparation, ſhall bee named Aduenturers, and ſhall haue the one halfe of all ſuche Landes, Territories, Townes, Mynes of golde and ſiluer, and other Mettalles whatſoeuer that ſhal be found, gotten, obtained, and conquered by this diſcouerie: yeeldyng to her Maieſtie one fift parte of all their part golde and ſiluer, as ſhall happen to be had out of any Mynes that ſo ſhall be founde.</p>
            <p>That thoſe parties which doe employe themſelues perſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nally in the preſent diſcouerie, ſhall be named Enterpriſers, and ſhall haue the other halfe of all the Landes, Territories, Townes, Mynes of golde and ſiluer, and other Mettalles, yeeldyng to her Maieſtie the fift part of the golde and ſiluer, as the Aduenturers doe: The ſame to bee diſtributed by the Generall, with the conſent of the greateſt part of twelue diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>creete perſons to bee choſen out of the whole number of En<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terpriſers.</p>
            <p>Alſo, that all trade of Marchaundize whiche ſhall bee vſed to and from thoſe partes, whiche by this diſcouerie ſhall bee founde out, ſhall appertaine onely to the Aduentures whiche firſt ſhall diſburce their money for this diſcouerie, with prohi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bition to all other her Maieſties Subiectes and other Mar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chauntes to deale in the ſaied partes, without the conſent of the firſt Aduenturers, vpon loſſe of Shippe and goodes, and puniſhment of their perſons, that ſo ſhall aduenture in trade of Marchaundize: or otherwiſe by impriſonment at the Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>panies pleaſure.</p>
            <p>That no perſon ſhall hereafter aduenture in this diſcoue<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rie, as Aduenturers for the profites mentioned in the firſt Ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ticle, but ſuche onely as doe diſburce their money in this firſt preparation: and thei ſhall not aduenture hereafter any grea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter ſomme then ratablie accordyng to their proportion of this their firſt aduenture.</p>
            <p>
               <pb facs="tcp:173767:9"/>
Alſo, the profite whiche by this diſcouerie ſhall be attained vnto, either by lande whiche maie be conquered, or otherwiſe gotten: as alſo ſuche profite whiche by this diſcouerie ſhal be obtained by Mynes, or otherwiſe gotten, that eache one ſhall haue his parte rate and rate like: according to the proportion of their firſt aduenture, and not otherwiſe.</p>
            <p>The Aduenturers in this firſt preparation, ſhall at their owne free will and libertie, chooſe whether thei will ſupplie hereafter any further charge or not: if there doe fall out any ſuche occaſion to require the ſame. And yet withall ſhall for euer holde to them the freedome of the trade whiche ſhall growe in any of theſe partes. Notwithſtandyng their ſaied refuſall to beare any further charge.</p>
            <p>That in the Patent whiche is to be obtained, be graunted that all her Maieſties ſubiectes, maie tranſporte themſelues thether that ſhall be contented to goe. And that the patented or his aſſignes maie ſhippe thether from tyme to tyme, ſo ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny and ſuche perſons, men, women and children, as thei ſhall thinke meete. And the ſame perſons to inhabite or remaine there at their pleaſure, any law to the contrarie notwithſtan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dyng, with expreſſe prohibition as is mentioned in the third Article, againſt all others whiche ſhall goe thether without the licence of the patented or his aſſignes firſt obtained.</p>
            <p>That it ſhall not be lawfull for any of her Maieſties ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſectes, or any other to enhabite or traffique within twoo hun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dred Leagues any waie of the place, where the Generall ſhal haue ſettled his cheefeſt beyng or reſidence.</p>
         </div>
         <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
